<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>YAPB</title>
		<description>Yet another pointless blog.</description>
		<link>http://wudong.github.io</link>
		<atom:link href="http://wudong.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>Mock the Life in the UK Test</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;So I have passed the &lt;strong&gt;Life in the UK Test&lt;/strong&gt;, oh yeah! But to be fair, it is quite simple;
I have prepared for the worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People (my solicitor especially) are saying that even native Britons wont be able to pass the Life
in the UK Test without preparation, which I kinda of agree. After all, who on earth would try to remember
 &lt;em&gt;where did Henry VIII&amp;#39;s fifth wife come from?&lt;/em&gt;
But with some time studying and remembering, it become fairly simple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I guess The government has no intention to
train each immigrant to be &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b006z736&quot;&gt;egghead&lt;/a&gt;,
or drive away every possible candidates!
The 40 minutes test took me 15 minutes to finish with double check,
and hesitating whether to do a triple check to make the &lt;strong&gt;£50&lt;/strong&gt; test fee more worthwhile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In retrospective, although the test in general can be defined as &amp;#39;piece of cake&amp;#39;,
I wish I could have better ways preparing it -- reading books is never fun for me, let
along reading one that filled with pretty much unrelated facts. Most people
passing the test say it would be enough to just finished the question book, that
is most likely to be true according to my experience, although nobody can be certain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then did a google and  I was amazed that
by the look of the sheer number of the websites, it is a quite competitive niche.&lt;br&gt;
Almost all the websites that are made for the Life in the UK Test,
are pretty much static site that full of all kinda of strange questions and advertise.
It is in a way, worth than the book, &lt;em&gt;which make me quite sad&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sadness left me think if I can do better. Although I am not really
a website person, I had always wanted to do something; now it might be finally a good reason.
I wanted to see if I can take a different approach and achieve better results than
the other websites alike, and get some experience on how a website
really work (i.e., make money).
With that passionate thought and a few sleepless weekends (I do have a proper day job unfortunately)
the website &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.testlifeinuk.com&quot;&gt;Life UK Test&lt;/a&gt; come to life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wife is pretty much happy with it, I am pretty much happy with it, then I found
I have hit a brick wall. Google does not want to rank me, despite all the fancy
tricks I have put in and the fact that the website is built with AngularJs, a framework from Google!
This simply means &lt;strong&gt;No One&lt;/strong&gt; will ever to be able to dig it out and use it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 19 Jun 2014 13:08:26 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>http://wudong.github.io/personal/2014/06/19/life-in-the-uk-test.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://wudong.github.io/personal/2014/06/19/life-in-the-uk-test.html</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
